You're listening to the AI Native Dev,
brought to you by Tesler.
Hello and welcome back. In this episode,
we are going to be talking with James
Ward once again. Hello James.
Hello. Thanks for having me.
Welcome back to the podcast. It's been
seconds since we last chatted.
And this is a follow-on episode where
we're going to get a little bit more
hands-on and we're going to take a look
at a tool from AWS called Q Developer.
James, first of all, before we jump into
dive straight into the screen share,
tell us a little bit about Q Developer
and you know, some of the capabilities.
Yeah, and I should caveat this with I'm
new to AWS, just getting into these
tools. And so I'm not an expert on them.
I'm learning and it's been fun to to
learn these tools and start integrating
them into how I write code. But here's
the high level as I understand it is
that Q Developer is an AI assistant.
There is IDE plugin, so IntelliJ, VS
Code. I don't know if there's other IDEs
supported. And then there is in the AWS
console. So if you're managing your
cloud infrastructure in AWS, there's
also a Q console in there that you can
chat with and ask questions like list my
EC2 instances or something. So there's
it's integrated there. And then there's
also a command line version of Q
Developer. And so that's that is my
potentially wrong understanding of it.
There's
No, I
I've seen that. I've seen all the
details, but I've seen that actually.
That's really interesting. The basically
the CLI style Q Developer. I have seen
that. And actually, yeah, I've heard a
few people mention actually that Q
Developer is particularly great when you
have you're already using AWS services
and you're coding against AWS APIs and
things like that. And it's very well
finely tuned on those kind of APIs and
integrations.
Yeah, I think so. And I've used it some
for that. So, I was working on a Kotlin
Conf talk and was asking Q developer
like, "How do I do this with the AWS SDK
for Kotlin?" And the answers it was
coming up with were pretty good and
helpful. So, I don't know the specifics
on how it's trained if it is more
weighted on on AWS specific things. But
I'll go on and ask it like questions
about regex and questions about I was
just asking it about the pickle
configuration language. And it was it
has general knowledge as well.
So, I think it's not just about it's not
just for AWS use.
No, no. You can use it as a general
purpose developer tool.
Absolutely.
Let's bring your screen up, James. There
we go. And and we can jump in and show
us a little bit about how you're using
it here. And this is this looks like cuz
this is
Yeah, I should give a This is IntelliJ
IDEA, yep. And with some Java code. And
maybe as a as some background for this
project that I'm in. This is has been
one place where I have used Q developer
because I've been writing some code
which is going into a space of things
that I do not understand, which is how
do I use Java with Loom with a
structured task scope and do structured
concurrency in Java. And so, I was able
to write this code and it and Q
developer did help me on some of the
aspects of this. But I want to walk
through some of the kind of just things
that I've used it for. And again, I'm
not an expert on Q developer. I'm still
new to it and and learning. But one of
the things
I should say as well, for those who are
only listening to the podcast wondering
what they should be looking at. We're on
YouTube, so these episodes are best
viewed on YouTube. But above all
absolutely continue listening as well
and you'll be able to you'll be able to
hopefully understand what we're doing on
the in the IDE, but you'll have to use
your imagination or you can go to
YouTube for the full experience.
Yeah.
Sorry, James.
Yeah, no, good thing to highlight. You
want to be able to see this.
Okay, there's a few things that I've
used Q developer for that that have
actually helped me be more productive.
And so, the first one is that there are
times that I pull up a piece of code and
maybe even I wrote the code, but but I
don't actually understand the code. This
happens for me a lot with Rust and
Python languages that I'm not as
familiar with where I can look at the
code and I can tell myself and be like,
"I don't might be able to understand
what's going on there." But, here's what
what I do a lot with code that I'm not
familiar with, especially in unfamiliar
programming languages, is I just
highlight a block of code and then I go
to explain code. And so, now this will
look at my code that I just highlighted
and be like, "Okay, here's all the
things that are happening and here's the
like try-with-resources and why that's
happening and then But, the usually the
summary is one of the more useful pieces
is that what this code actually is
doing, which isn't totally clear in the
Java version of this one. It's more
clear in some of the other versions I've
written of this code, is that it's doing
what we call a race where it's it's
making two concurrent HTTP requests to
the same URL and then it's returning the
response from the first result that
completes successfully. And I don't
know, for me like pretty impressive that
it was able to look at this code which
which is using these forks and a join
and then understand actually what was
the goal of this particular piece of
code. And but yeah, the explain
functionality is certainly useful. And
then of course, you can come in and ask
follow-up questions and all that kind of
stuff. So, I think that helping me
understand a code base is helpful.
And and this is super useful even for
whether whether you're an advanced
developer or an experienced developer,
just reading someone else's code is
hard. If me reading my own code from
about 2 months ago is hard enough. But
but also code reviews, this is super
useful from a code review point of view
as well, right? Because it's
particularly if it's a larger block of
code, you don't need to go through it
line by line. You just want to
understand the gist and then I and then
identify identify the the the the key
places.
Yep. Yep. Exactly. Yeah, so I think that
understanding a code base super helpful.
You can also feed in error messages and
be like explain this error message and
so there's just a lot of places that
that I'm like, okay, I need to increase
my understanding on this and using that
the chat console to explore that has
been useful.
Mhm.
So that's one of the areas you you may
have seen and when I right clicked on
this block of code that there was also
some other things in here. I can do a
refactor fix which hopefully there's
nothing to fix in my code cuz it's
always perfect. But I So I haven't used
that one a whole lot.
Optimize code and then send a prompt. So
send a prompt is just like you want to
ask whatever about that block of code
and so one of the things that we can do
is say write a test for this code. And
we can see how it does with that. I
haven't actually tested this before but
and like we talked about in the previous
episode, I don't have the LM right my
test usually but some people may want
that and yeah, so great. We're going to
J unit five Makita test for that and I
have no idea if that code works but we
could go over flip over to our test file
and insert that test in and and actually
see if it does what we expect it to.
Yeah, and this is an area as well as
documentation other things where
developers don't necessarily spend a lot
of their time like adding those
necessary tests at the end. I think this
is a key area that actually will make
projects more complete from an AI point
of view by providing us these I think we
we talked about in the other in in the
last episode as well. The tedium parts
of a developer's role that they actually
don't want to focus too much time on
because they want to stay doing things
that they find interesting or creative.
Like we're I tend to do a little bit
more of a TDD style approach to how I
code. But,
for those that don't, probably the
reason why you want to write a test for
something is maybe you're still
iterating on it, figuring it out, and
you just want to like get some
boilerplate test stuff there. But,
probably the more valuable thing there
is that you haven't written your test,
but you figure that I might as well have
the test be to prevent regressions in
the future. So, that could definitely be
a viable thing. You've got some existing
functionality. Let's get a test set up.
Let's make sure it passes. And then that
will help ensure that I'm not going to
regress on anything there.
Absolutely. And I think the human aspect
of this is very good as well, cuz I
think there's a number of places that
kind of create test suites and things
like that, but it's a very broad attack
on a code base. Whereas, with this,
let's say this scenario one method is
one that we understand is a very key and
important golden path area that like
like you said previously as well, may
get hundreds of thousands or millions of
pass-throughs through various
transactions or something. And we need
this to be bulletproof. We can like
select various pieces and say, "Look,
these are the areas that I want you to
generate tests for me or what or help me
assist me in in in building tests for
this code." So, I think this is still a
very nice piece of human interaction,
human assistant with AI.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, so that's the the kind of
highlight and explain or pop over into
chat and do that for. The other one that
I think is probably the most common use
of these AI assistants is just
generating blocks of code for me. And
so, this is a fun one where I've got all
these different scenarios here. And
let's say that I want to now start
writing my 11th scenario. We'll see if
this works, but usually as I'm starting
to write, let's see if it string.
And sometimes it's hey, do you Oh, there
we go. Okay. So, so it did I had to
start getting a little further in, but
it's okay. Now, I'm underneath scenario
10 and it's already guessed, "Hey, what
you want next is scenario 11." So, it
like figured out which And then what's
weird is if I start typing this like
after scenario one, then the code hint
from Q developer is 1A. And so, it's
wild that it like understands where I am
in this code and starts like giving me
this like multi-line completion.
That's That's really interesting cuz a
lot Depending on understanding the
position you are and understanding what
comes before and what comes after is not
something that every assistant does. And
I think it's really important,
particularly if you're in a method or
something like that as well, but
Yeah.
that context is really is really good to
see.
Yeah. And so, I've I think that my kind
of acceptance rate on these is generally
pretty low. Like, often times the code
that I'm writing like I've already got
the code in my head that I want to
write. And so, it's not very hard to
actually just a mash out the characters,
but it There have been times where the
code that hints that come up in here,
I'm totally shocked by. I'm like, "How
did it know that was exactly what I
wanted to write?" And so, yeah, I I've
found definitely some value in the code
hinting stuff, especially when I'm in
like boilerplate code land. But, I tend
to write a lot of code in Scala and and
Kotlin where there's not a lot of
boilerplate. And so, I don't know. For
me, the like multi-line completion
sometimes is really helpful and provides
a lot of value. And other times,
Yeah.
just is a a little bit of a distraction
from me just like mashing out the code
that's already in my head.
Yeah, yeah. Oh, amazing. Amazing. Yeah,
this looks good.
obviously it does have that
functionality.
Which is I think common across most of
the AI assistants.
Yeah, so there's that. There's a couple
of features in here for these slash
commands. So, I have not used these that
much, but slash dev plan and implement
new functionality across multiple files.
I don't know what I I
I'm sure that's useful. I haven't dove
into that yet. There's transform if I
have a project that I want to upgrade
the Java version of. And I've heard
people using that and that being
helpful. And then there's a new one
which which I I just filed a bug
yesterday cuz it doesn't actually work
yet in for my setup and it's probably
because I'm like on NYX OS which is
weird version of Linux and I don't have
a GPU. But anyways, what this at
workspace does is it's supposed to allow
me to ask questions about the whole
entire project. And so I should be able
to say summarize what this project does.
And then it's supposed to have actually
built a like local vector database of my
whole entire project. And yeah, it's I'm
still indexing. So this is I just filed
the bug on this yesterday cuz it's I'm
still indexing the project. So I don't
know why it's not succeeding indexing on
my weird weird NYX OS Linux machine. But
I think once that actually works for me,
that'll be something that'll be
interesting to be able to ask questions
about my project specifically. So
With a much greater a much greater scope
of context which will provide you with a
more accurate answers than if you were
just to look at a small
Just at a single file or something.
Yeah.
Yeah, and the place where I use Q chat a
lot and you people use Copilot and and
chat GPT or Claude models for this is
it's just like trying to understand a
concept that I'm not familiar with. And
so I'm going to try something which I
haven't tried which I'll be interested
to see see how this does. But what this
project is doing is it's doing these
races of these HTTP calls. And so I'm
just totally curious if I say write a
Java method
that races two HTTP
requests
and only
returns the first
first successful
result.
I'm just totally curious if it's going
to come up with anything like what I
what I have here.
But this is exactly like when I'm
venturing into new territory,
concepts I don't understand, I just have
a full-on conversation with Q now. And
okay, so it didn't use the
No, it hasn't used the same code that
you did in
It didn't use the new structured task
scope, which this is like a brand new
Java thing. So probably this is trained
on the training data set is much more
heavy on completable future than on this
on the structured task scope. So let me
ask a follow-up. Can you do that using
the structured task scope?
And we'll see if it So structured task
scope is the new structured concurrency
stuff in Java, which I think is still
experimental. So I'm venturing into some
pretty uncharted territory. Oh,
There we go. There we go.
with code that looks pretty similar to
mine. So I had to give it a little bit
of nudging to use the the new APIs
instead of the old APIs, but
What I like
at the bottom of that as well, it's
actually if you scroll down a touch, not
only did it provide the answer plus a
description as to why it works. Keep
scrolling. It It provided
Oh, a difference on the differences
between the completable future and the
structured task scope.
Actually, what I was looking for was I
think the previous one had a reference
over to Stack Overflow, interestingly.
So it's it's nice to be able to almost
like give you references of
Yeah.
of others
Yeah, the
similar questions that have been put up.
Cuz then you get again, it's almost like
that human involvement or if you don't
if you want to
talk to someone with that that has
has had that problem and understanding
their opinion on Stack Overflow versus
general LLM.
In my experience with Stack Overflow a
lot of times is
there's the accepted answer and then
there's the like highest upvoted answer.
And so it's I do like that I can then go
open up the Stack Overflow and see is it
what it's telling me the accepted answer
or the the most upvoted or some
somewhere in between or
So yeah, it is nice to have those
references.
And that's where we are with LLMs as
well. And a lot of the time if it has a
lot of training data on a in a specific
way, chances are it's going to provide
you that way versus something which is
potentially better unless there's some
fine-tuning or altered data sets that it
trains from.
Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah. And so that's the ways that I've
been using Q Developer at least in in
the IDE. When I'm in the AWS console,
I'm asking it about how I set up my
CloudFormation
things and asking it questions about my
resources. And so that's a bit
different. But this is where I'm using Q
Developer most is within my IntelliJ IDE
writing Java, Kotlin, Scala mostly,
sometimes Rust or Python
And yeah, it definitely has has been
helpful in in especially as I am moving
into areas that I am unfamiliar with.
That's when it seems to have had the
most value for me.
Yeah. Amazing.
James, this has been great to great to
chat and actually get to get to see some
get to see some real world Q Developer
in in some live demos. So thank you.
Thank you very much for that. people
wanted to learn more, go and try it out,
what's their best route to do that?
There is a web page on the AWS site.
It's like Q Developer and here's how to
get started with IntelliJ or VS Code or
whatever. And or you can just like in
IntelliJ go to your plugins and go
install it. And then yeah, once you
install the plugin in IntelliJ, then
start asking questions. There's like a
slash help menu. I don't know. You can I
wonder if you can also ask it like,
like, what should I use Q developer for?
Like conversationally learn how to use
it by
It's This is the future, right? We just
like like experiment with with this AI
assistant and and see what it comes up
with.
Yeah.
Actually, you know, oh, I should mention
that Q developer is free for developers.
I
There's like a a free edition and that's
the one I'm using. So, yeah. I think
that I think I'm using it for free. I
think you just need
a AWS account or something.
Amazing. Thank you very much, James, and
appreciate your insights into Q
developer and thanks for the double
session that you gave.
Yeah. Yeah, thanks for having me.
Thanks for tuning in. Join us next time
on the AI Native Dev, brought to you by
TestAI.